Balcomb and Gertrude Greene
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Writings, circa 1927-1984, Series 4:; (Boxes 1-3; 2.1 linear ft.)
  - By Balcomb Greene, circa 1927-1979, 4.1:
    - Books (Box 1)
      - Untitled (proposal, outline, and first draft), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Journal Entries, 1942-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Lecture Notes - Carnegie Institute of Technology (Box 1)
      - "Classicism - Romanticism," circa 1942-1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - "The Dance in 17th and 18th Centuries," circa 1942-1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - "General Pittsburgh Notes - A," circa 1942-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - "HAC [History of Art and Culture], 1st Sem.", 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - "HAC [History of Art and Culture], second semester plan," circa 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - "Medieval and Renaissance Music," 1953-1954, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
      - "Modern Painting, first sem.," circa 1942-1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - "MSCN" (Modern), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Neo-Classicism - Realism, and "The Arts in Modern Times, 1870- ," 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - "Pre-History - Gothic," 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - "Renaissance and Reformation," 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Lecture Notes - Dartmouth College, Literature Course, circa 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Notes and Fragments (Box 2)
      - Fiction, circa 1927-1930s (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Non-Fiction, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 3-8)
    - Novels (Box 2)
      - "As the River Flows or No Middle Ground," circa 1930s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
      - "The Fothering Manner," circa 1930s, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
      - "The Girdle," circa 1930s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
      - "It's 57th Street" (outline, list of characters, fragments), circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - "It's Love and Revolution" (outline for a rewrite of "Revolt Out of Town"), 1948, (See also: box 2, folders 25-26) (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - "The Poem Thud" (manuscript and drafts), circa 1930s, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 20-24)
      - "Revolt Out of Town," circa 1930s, (3 folders; See also: box 2, folder 19) (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
      - "Women Under the Aspens," circa 1927-1930 (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
    - Poems (Box 3)
      - Numbered (1-68), undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - Titled (A-Z) and Untitled, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Themes of Love, Death, and the Sea, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Submitted to The Paris Review, 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Short Stories (A-Z by title), circa 1930s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Student Writings (Box 3)
      - Course Notes, NYU, Classical - Modern, with Charts, circa 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Course Notes, NYU, Foundations of Modern Art (Prof. Dmitri Tselos), circa 1940-1942, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
      - Course Notes, NYU, includes "History of Criticism" and "Rubens," circa 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Course Notes, NYU, "Italian Painting..Tables?and notes of," circa 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Course Notes, NYU, Review Outlines (Egyptian - Greek and Roman), circa 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Paper, NYU, Principles of Modern Art (Prof. Dmitri Tselos) "The 'Machine Esthetic' - Sources," 1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Paper, NYU, "The Mechanized Human Figure in Painting from 1909-1921," 1942 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Papers and Course Notes, NYU, "Art History..general Papers and notes.." (includes "The Mechanized Human Figure in Painting from 1909-1921"), circa 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Thesis, NYU, "Mechanistic Tendencies in Painting from 1901-1908," 1942 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - By Gertrude Greene, circa 1951, 2:
    - List of Paintings and Constructions, circa 1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - By Other Authors, circa 1959-1984, 3:
    - About Balcomb Greene, circa 1959-1960, 1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Greene, Terryn Trimpen (notes for interview)
      Sager, Anne. "Balcomb" (poem)
      Sandler, Irving. Untitled (statement)
      Seldin, Sylvia. "Balcomb Greene" (student paper)
      Unidentified Catalog Entry
    - About Balcomb and Gertrude Greene (Box 3)
      - Lippman, Carol. "Balcomb and Gertrude Greene: Mutual Influences" (student paper), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - About Gertrude Greene (Box 3)
      - Moss, Jacqueline. "The Constructions of Gertrude Greene" (M.A. Thesis, Queens College, City University of New York, 1980), circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Unidentified (by Moss?), undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
        "Gertrude Greene, 1904-1956"
        "Gertrude Greene, Constructions, Collages, Paintings"
- Art Work, 1976, Series 5:; (Box 3; 2 folders)
  Art work consists of a collage, one drawing, and a sketchbook. The collage, composed of a black and white photographic print with paper and paint, probably was executed by Balcomb Greene. The drawing, signed H[?]. R., is of a seated female nude. Balcomb Greene's sketchbook contains two drawings dated January 1976; the remaining pages of the volume are blank.
  - Collage and Drawing, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Sketchbook, 1976, (1 volume) (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Register of Paintings, undated, Series 6:; (Box 3; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Balcomb Greene's register of paintings bears evidence of the 1996 fire that destroyed his Montauk studio, and it is likely that portions did not survive. A separate page for each completed painting contains a small photograph or sketch, with the title, date of execution, and code or negative number indicated. Many pages include notes relating to exhibitions, loans, and ownership; some contain the notation "destroyed."
  Sheets documenting works executed during the periods 1941-1948, 1963-1964, and 1980-1982 are the least damaged sections of the register. The remaining portion consists of partial pages missing titles, dates of execution, and other salient information.
  - Register of Paintings (executed 1941-1982), undated, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 24-29)
- Printed Material, circa 1930-2009, Series 7:; (Boxes 4-7, 11, and OV 12; 3.9 linear ft.)
  Issues of Art Front are dated 1934-1938. Balcomb Greene served on the magazine's editorial board during 1935-1936 and contributed articles during that period. Modern Art by Katherine S. Dreier is Greene's well-used copy; his name is inscribed on the flyleaf, and affixed inside the front cover is a copy of a newspaper review.
  Articles by Balcomb Greene were published in Art Front, College Art Journal and other periodicals. Some representative titles are: "The Function of Leger," "The Problem of Expression in Art," "Basic Concepts for Teaching Art," and "The Doctrine of Pure Aesthetic."
  Exhibition catalogs and articles from newspapers and periodicals represent the majority of the printed material about or mentioning Balcomb and Gertrude Greene. Museum publications consist of annual reports, bulletins and newsletters.
  Among the miscellaneous items pertaining to Balcomb and Gertrude Greene are a program for a house tour that included Greene's home, biographical notes about the University Center in Virginia's visiting fellows, a calendar and book of postcards reproducing art work.
  - Art Front, 1934-1938, (oversized material housed in box 11) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - By Katherine S. Dreier. Modern Art, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - By Balcomb Greene (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1936, (See: Art Front, box 1, folder 1, and box 11) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Articles, 1948-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters to the Editor, 1967-1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - By Terryn Greene - Letters to the Editor, 1968-1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - About/Mentioning Balcomb and Gertrude Greene (Box 4)
    - Advertisements and Listings (Box 4)
      - Balcomb Greene, 1951-2003, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Balcomb and Gertrude Greene, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Gertrude Greene, 1981-2007 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Articles - Newspaper Clippings (Box 4)
      - Balcomb Greene, circa 1930-2005, undated, (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 10-15)
      - Gertrude Greene, 1956-1991 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Articles - Periodicals (Box 4)
      - Balcomb Greene, 1940-1991, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
      - Balcomb and Gertrude Greene, 1976-1988 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Gertrude Greene, 1951-1981 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Auction Catalogs (Box 4)
      - Balcomb Greene, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Balcomb and Gertrude Greene, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Books (Box 4)
      - Hale, Robert Beverly and Niké Hale. The Art of Balcomb Greene, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Ritchie, Andrew Carnduff. Abstract Painting and Sculpture in America (Balcomb and Gertrude included), 1951 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Collection Catalogs (Box 4)
      - Balcomb Greene, 1942-1977, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 26-29)
      - Balcomb and Gertrude Greene, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, Announcements, etc. (Box 4)
      - Balcomb Greene 1941-1946, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
      - Balcomb Greene, 1947-1963, (16 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-16)
      - Balcomb Greene, 1964-2009, undated, (14 folders; oversized material housed in box 11 and OV 12) (Box 6, Folder 1-14)
      - Balcomb and Gertrude Greene, 1938-1983, (6 folders) (Box 6, Folder 15-20)
      - Balcomb and Gertrude Greene, 1986-2007, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
      - Gertrude Greene, 1951-2007, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
    - Miscellaneous Items, 1959-1981, (oversized material housed in box 11) (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Museum Publications, 1959-1981, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    - Reproductions of Art Work by Balcomb Greene, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Printed Material, 1934-1966, undated, (See also: box 4, folder 1; box 6, folder 4; box 7, folder 6) (Box 11)
  - Oversized Printed Material (exhibition poster), 1973 (Box OV 12)
- Audio-visual Recordings, 1963-1990, Series 8:; (Box 7; 0.3 linear ft.)
  Recordings consist of interviews with Balcomb Greene, a video recording documenting Greene's 1990 memorial service, and a "McCarthy tape." During the 1968 presidential campaign, both Balcomb and Terryn Greene were supporters of Eugene McCarthy, and Terryn was involved with organizing "Montauk's Day for McCarthy." Audio recordings are on 3 sound tape reels (7 in., 5 in., and 4 in. tape).
  - Balcomb Greene interviewed by Marian Gore for "The Art Scene," KPFK radio, Los Angeles, 1963, (1 sound tape reel) (Box 7, Folder 10, Item 1)
  - Balcomb Greene interviewed by Karl E. Fortess, 1975, (1 sound tape reel) (Box 7, Folder 10, Item 2)
  - "McCarthy tape," circa 1968, (1 sound tape reel) (Box 7, Folder 10, Item 3)
  - "Balcomb Greene Memorial Service at the Parrish [Museum]," 1990, (1 videocassette: VHS) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Balcomb Greene, guest on "Sarasota Forum: Balcomb Greene, Artist" and "50 Years of Painting," The Harmon Gallery, Naples, FL, 1980, undated, (2 videocassettes: U-matic) (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Photographs, circa 1880s-1996, Series 9:; (Boxes 7-10; 2.6 linear ft.)
  Photographs are of art work, events, exhibition installations, miscellaneous subjects, people, and places.
  Around 1940, Balcomb became interested in photography. He did not develop his own film, but preferred to produce the prints himself. He sometimes used photographs as notes for planning paintings and often experimented with lighting to produce different effects. It is highly likely that Balcomb took many of the photographs of his own and Gertrude's work that survive among their papers. Many of the photographs - especially those of art work - bear evidence of smoke and water damage sustained in the 1996 fire that destroyed Balcomb Greene's studio.
  Photographs of people include Balcomb Greene, Gertrude Greene, Terryn Greene, family, friends and other individuals (identified and unidentified). There are pictures of Balcomb with fellow students, friends, juries, and Terryn; one photograph of Balcomb with others [probably artist colleagues] is by Hans Namuth. Also found are photographs of three generations of the Greene family showing Balcomb as a young boy (identified as John Wesley or Wesley on the prints), and a few of his mother's relatives.
  Events include photographic documentation of the damage caused by the 1996 fire that destroyed Balcomb Greene's studio. Miscellaneous subjects are Greene's Rolls Royce, and pet cats and dogs.
  Places recorded are: Greene's boyhood homes and churches in New York, Iowa, and unidentified locations; his mother's family house; Gertrude and Balcomb's cottage in Hopewell Junction, New York, where they spent summers before building their house at Montauk; the Greenes' house at Montauk; Gertrude's studio; travel pictures of Europe and Asia; and unidentified interiors.
  Also found in this series are a small number of negatives, 35-mm slides, and color transparencies that document art work, miscellaneous subjects, people, and places.
  - Art Work by Balcomb Greene (Box 7)
    - Paintings (executed circa 1930-1954), undated, (20 folders) (Box 7, Folder 13-32)
    - Paintings (executed 1955-1986), undated (Box 8, Folder 1-30)
    - Paintings (A-Z by title), undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Paintings, Unidentified (Box 8)
      - Geometric Abstractions, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 32-33)
      - Abstract Compositions, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 34-35)
      - Figures and Heads, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 36-37)
      - Seascapes and Landscapes, undated (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Art Work by Gertrude Greene (Box 8)
    - Constructions (A-Z, by title; executed circa 1935-1946), undated (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Constructions and Paintings, Unidentified, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 40-41)
    - Paintings (A-Z, by title; executed 1946-1956, undated), undated (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Sculpture (executed circa 1932-1940s), 1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Drawings of Sculpture, undated (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Events (Box 9)
    - Ramsey Clark Congressional Campaign visits Montauk,1974 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Montauk Studio Fire Damage, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Installations (Balcomb Greene) (Box 9)
    - ACA Galleries, New York, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Arlene Bujese Gallery, East Hampton, NY, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Harmon-Meeks Gallery, Naples, Florida, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
    - Oceanic Institute, Bay Harbor Island, Florida, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Phoenix Gallery, Washington, DC, 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Saidenberg Gallery, New York, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified Venues, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Installations (Balcomb and Gertrude Greene) (Box 9)
    - Katharina Rich Perlow Gallery, New York, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Installations (Gertrude Greene) (Box 9)
    - American Abstract Artists, Squibb Gallery, San Antonio, 1937, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects (Box 9)
    - Automobile, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Pets, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
  - People (Box 9)
    - Balcomb Greene, circa 1914-1980s, (8 folders) (Box 9, Folder 16-23)
    - Balcomb Greene with Others (Box 9)
      - With Family, (see: Greene Family, box 9, folders 36 and 40) (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Class Pictures, 1912-1913, undated (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - With Syracuse University Fencing Club, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - With Friends aboard Ship, circa 1931-1932 (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - With Friends at Montauk House (during construction), circa 1947 (Box 9, Folder 28)
      - With Terryn Trimpen Greene, circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 29)
      - With Fashion Model in Studio (for Ladies' Home Journal feature article, Jan.-Feb. 1963 issue), circa 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 30)
      - With Colleagues (Hans Namuth, photographer) and with Exhibition Jury, undated (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Gertrude Glass Greene, circa 1940s-1956 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Terryn Trimpen Greene, circa 1960s, undated (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Greene Family (Box 9)
      - Bertram Stillman Greene, circa 1880s-1929 (Box 9, Folder 34)
      - Bertram Stillman Greene and Florence Stover Greene, circa 1890s-1907 (Box 9, Folder 35)
      - Bertram Stillman Greene and/or Florence Stover Greene with their Children (John Wesley [Balcomb], Fidelia, and Dorothy), circa 1905-1920 (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Clayton Greene, circa 1900 (Box 9, Folder 37)
      - Dorothy Greene, circa 1918 and circa 1923 (Box 9, Folder 38)
      - Harvey S. Greene, 19th century (Box 9, Folder 39)
      - John Wesley [Balcomb], with sisters Fidelia, and Dorothy Greene, circa 1905-circa 1910 (Box 9, Folder 40)
      - Groups (identified family members), circa 1900-circa 1907 (Box 9, Folder 41)
      - Groups (unidentified family members), 19th century-1900s (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Others (Box 9)
      - Individuals (identified), 1925-1953, undated (Box 9, Folder 43)
        Murel Ashley
        Roy Cavert
        Sen Chow Hone
        Lee Hultzen
        Thorpe McClusky
        Hiroshe Shinidzu
        Eric and Judith
      - Individuals and Groups (unidentified), 1961-1980, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 44-45)
  - Places (Box 9)
    - Boyhood Homes and Churches (Box 9)
      - Millville, New York, circa 1900, undated (Box 9, Folder 46)
      - Arthur, Iowa, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 47)
      - Unidentified Location, undated (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Mother's Family House ("Stover Farm House"), New York, circa 1900 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Greene's House at Montauk, New York (Box 9)
      - Construction, circa 1947 (Box 9, Folder 50)
      - Exterior, circa 1950s-1970 (Box 9, Folder 51)
      - Exterior after Snow Storm, undated (Box 9, Folder 52)
      - Interior, circa 1947-1970s (Box 9, Folder 53)
      - Studio (pre-fire), undated (Box 9, Folder 54)
      - Studio (fire damage), 1996, (See: Events - Montauk Studio Fire Damage, Box 9, folder 46) (Box 9, Folder 55)
      - Montauk Landscapes (includes 1978 storm damage), 1978, undated (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Greene's Summer Cottage, Hopewell Junction, New York, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Gertrude Greene's Studio, New York City, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Travel Pictures (Box 9)
      - Asia, undated (Box 9, Folder 59)
      - Europe, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 60-61)
    - Unidentified Interiors,undated (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Negatives (Box 10)
    - Art Work (by Balcomb Greene) (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - People (Balcomb Greene, unidentified individuals), undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Greene's Summer Cottage at Hopewell Junction, New York, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Travel Pictures (unidentified), undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Models, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Pets (cats), undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Slides (35 mm), undated, (slide box 1) (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Art Work by Balcomb Greene (paintings, A-Z by title; unidentified paintings, executed 1934-1971) (Box 10)
  - Slides (35 mm), undated, (slide box 2) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Art Work by Balcomb Greene (unidentified paintings, executed 1971-1982)
    Art Work by Gertrude Greene (unidentified)
    Art Work by Other Artists (paintings, A-Z, by artist, and unidentified; sculpture, unidentified)
    Miscellaneous Subjects (dog)
    People (Terryn Trimpen Greene)
    Places (Greene's house at Montauk; buildings in New York, Pittsburgh, and Philadelphia, identified by architect)
  - Transparencies (art work by Balcomb Greene), undated (Box 10, Folder 9)